Arthur Gleason Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Arthur Gleason Papers 1863-1931 (bulk 1900-1923)
MSS18382
Gleason, Arthur, 1878-1923
3,000 items
13 containers
5.2 linear feet
8 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Journalist, editor, and social reformer. Family and general correspondence, writings, subject files, clippings, and printed matter relating to Gleason's editorial work with Cosmopolitan, The Survey, and Collier's Weekly; his experiences as a journalist and medic in World War I; his activities on behalf of the British labor movement, Bureau of Industrial Research, United Mine Workers, and socialism; and his interest in topics such as immigration, Jews in the United States, American isolationism, the Irish question, and religious groups and sects in Southern California.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Addams, Jane, 1860-1935.; Baldwin, Roger N. (Roger Nash), 1884-1981--Correspondence.; Blankenhorn, John.; Bliven, Bruce, 1889-1977.; Bok, Edward William, 1863-1930--Correspondence.; Brophy, John, 1883-1963.; Bruère, Robert W. (Robert Walter), 1876-1964.; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922.; Butler, Geoffrey G. (Geoffrey Gilbert), Sir, 1887-1929--Correspondence.; Carter, Edward C. (Edward Clark), 1878-1954--Correspondence.; Chesterton, G. K. (Gilbert Keith), 1874-1936.; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965--Correspondence.; Cohn, Fannia M. (Fannia Mary), 1885- --Correspondence.; Cook, Joe, 1887-1959--Correspondence.; Croly, Herbert David, 1869-1930.; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926--Correspondence.; Eastman, George, 1854-1932--Correspondence.; Eaton, Walter Prichard, 1878-1957--Correspondence.; Edwards, Richard Henry, 1877-1954--Correspondence.; Fels, Joseph, 1854-1914--Correspondence.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence.; Furuseth, Andrew, 1854-1938.; Gannett, Lewis, 1891-1966--Correspondence.; Gleason family--Correspondence.; Gleason, Arthur, 1878-1923.; Gleason, Helen Hayes--Correspondence.; Grant, Percy Stickney, 1860-1927.; Hammer, Armand, 1898-1990--Correspondence.; Hapgood, Norman, 1868-1937--Correspondence.; Harcourt, Alfred, 1881-1954--Correspondence.; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946--Correspondence.; Hodges, Frank, 1887-1947.; Jusserand, J. J. (Jean Jules), 1855-1932--Correspondence.; Kellogg, Paul Underwood, 1879-1958--Correspondence.; Kirkup, Thomas, 1844-1912--Correspondence.; Krehbiel, Edward B. (Edward Benjamin), 1878- --Correspondence.; Laidler, Harry W. (Harry Wellington), 1884-1970--Correspondence.; Laski, Harold Joseph, 1893-1950--Correspondence.; Lewisohn, Ludwig, 1882-1955--Correspondence.; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974--Correspondence.; London, Jack, 1876-1916--Correspondence.; Lowell, A. Lawrence (Abbott Lawrence), 1856-1943--Correspondence.; Mack, Julian W. (Julian William), 1866-1943--Correspondence.; More, Paul Elmer, 1864-1937--Correspondence.; Morrow, William--Correspondence.; Oppenheim, James, 1882-1932--Correspondence.; Parkhurst, C. H. (Charles Henry), 1842-1933--Correspondence.; Percy of Newcastle, Eustace Percy, Baron, 1887-1958--Correspondence.; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943--Correspondence.; Phillips, John S. (John Sanburn), 1861-1949--Correspondence.; Robinson, Charles Mulford, 1869-1917--Correspondence.; Ross, Edward Alsworth, 1866-1951--Correspondence.; Scudder, Vida Dutton, 1861-1954.; Sinclair, May--Correspondence.; Smillie, Robert, 1857-1940.; Spalding, William Andrew, 1852-1941--Correspondence.; Steinmetz, Charles Proteus, 1865-1923.; Sullivan, Mark, 1874-1952--Correspondence.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Tolstoĭ, Ili︠a︡ L'vovich, graf, 1866-1933.; U'Ren, William Simon, 1859-1949--Correspondence.; Van Hise, Charles Richard, 1857-1918.; Wald, Lillian D., 1867-1940--Correspondence.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918--Correspondence.; Winter, William, 1836-1917--Correspondence.; Wise, Stephen S. (Stephen Samuel), 1874-1949--Correspondence.
Organizations
Bureau of Industrial Research.; United Mine Workers of America.
Subjects
American periodicals.; Emigration and immigration.; Irish question.; Isolationism--United States.; Jews--United States.; Labor unions--Great Britain.; Labor unions.; Labor--Great Britain.; Socialism.; World War, 1914-1918--Journalists.; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care.
Places
California--Religion.
Titles
Collier's weekly.; Cosmopolitan.; Survey.
Occupations
Editors.; Journalists.; Reformers.
Provenance
The papers of Arthur Huntington Gleason, journalist, editor, and social reformer, were given to the Library of Congress in 1968 by his widow, Helen Hayes Gleason Johnson.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Arthur Gleason are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on eight reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1878, Dec. 14 Born, Newark, N.J.
1901 B.A., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1901 1903 Reporter, New York Tribune
1903 Manuscript editor, Cosmopolitan
1904 1907 Assistant editor, Country Life in America, The Survey
1908 1913 Associate editor, Collier's Weekly
1912 Married Helen Hayes
1914 1915 Red Cross worker, Hector Monro Ambulance Corps, Belgium
1916 1917 European correspondent, New York Tribune and Century Magazine
1917 Writer, Publicity Department, YMCA, American Expeditionary Forces
1919 English correspondent, The Survey Awarded Mons Star and Ribbon by the British War Office Published with Paul U. Kellogg British Labor and the War. New York: Boni and Liveright
1920 Returned to the United States Published What the Workers Want. New York: Harcourt, Brace, and Howe
1921 Published Workers' Education. New York: Bureau of Industrial Research
1921 1922 Staff member, Bureau of Industrial Research Collaborated with John Brophy in advancing miners' plan for nationalization of the coal industry
1923 Moved to San Diego, Calif.
1923, Dec. 30 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Arthur Huntington Gleason (1878-1923) span the years 1863-1931, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1900-1923. Consisting of family correspondence, general correspondence, writings file, subject file, and miscellany including clippings and printed matter, the papers chart Gleason's career from his graduation from Yale University to his death from spinal meningitis in 1923. Letters and related material document his early years as an editor with Cosmopolitan, The Survey, and Collier's Weekly, but the major part of the collection relates to his years in Europe, 1914-1920. Gleason and his wife Helen Hayes were among a group of youthful American writers who volunteered to perform humanitarian service on behalf of the Allies during the first years of World War I, and it is this phase and the subsequent years of reconstruction and political turmoil that are treated most prominently in the collection. By the time Gleason returned to the United States in 1920, he had become a student of the British labor movement as well as a veteran observer of combat, and his growing socialist convictions led him to a career in research and public relations work for various labor organizations.
The papers in this collection focus chiefly on World War I. As a journalist and ambulance worker for the Red Cross in Belgium, Gleason became a proponent of the Allied cause. In addition to reporting on Allied soldiers and Belgium's defeated populace, he relayed stories of German atrocities back to the United States and served as an intermediary for English writers seeking to influence public opinion in this country in favor of the English position. Manuscripts of two of these writers, G. K. Chesterton and James Bryce, are among the articles and interview transcripts which Gleason sent to the United States from England for publication, and he retained them in his papers. Also in the collection are exchanges with Geoffrey B. Butler, J. J. Jusserand, the French ambassador to Washington, and Baron Eustace Percy of Newcastle on issues such as the Irish question, American isolationism, and the political and social ramifications of immigration to the United States. The impact of ethnicity on the American character, a frequent postwar theme of Gleason's, was a topic which he addressed in a series of articles on the status of Jews in America published by Hearst's International. Pertinent to this series are letters he received in 1922-1923 from Felix Frankfurter, Ludwig Lewisohn, Walter Lippmann, Julian W. Mack, and Stephen Samuel Wise.
Following his return to the United States in 1920, Gleason worked on behalf of the Bureau of Industrial Research and John Brophy of the United Mine Workers. Papers relevant to this aspect of his life are contained in the Correspondence series, in the Subject File under Bureau of Industrial Research, and the Writings File. Among the individuals who appear either as correspondents or in biographical sketches are John Blankenhorn, Bruce Bliven, John Brophy, Robert W. Bruère, Herbert David Croly, Andrew Furuseth, Frank Hodges, Vida Dutton Scudder, Robert Smillie, and Norman Thomas. After 1922 Gleason turned to writing about the new civilization he believed was emerging in the Southwest and to the varieties of religious experience he saw in California. He also underwent a personal crisis as a writer which is documented in private reflections he titled "The Darker Side." These and similar holograph notes are contained in the Writings File, as are transcripts of interviews he conducted with Percy Stickney Grant, Charles Proteus Steinmetz, Ili︠a︡ L'vovich Tolstoĭ, Charles Richard Van Hise, and others.
The family correspondence, although a relatively small part of the collection, is a source of biographical data. Letters Gleason sent his mother in 1906 include critical comments on Jane Addams's personality, and a file for 1915 contains descriptions of Gleason in action as a medic and reporter on the Western Front. Also in the family correspondence are letters sent and received by Helen Hayes Gleason during the war and a few exchanges which Gleason sent or wrote during boyhood. Letters of condolence to Helen Hayes Gleason after her husband's death are located in the general correspondence as are papers generated during her compilation of The Book of Arthur Gleason (1929). The family correspondence includes a letter of 1863 sent by a deacon of Henry Ward Beecher's Plymouth Congregational Church in Brooklyn to Gleason's maternal grandmother requesting that she accept an offer to fill Beecher's pulpit temporarily in his absence.
Correspondents include Roger N. Baldwin, Edward William Bok, Geoffrey G. Butler, Edward C. Carter, Sir Winston Churchill, Fannia M. Cohn, Joe Cook, Eugene V. Debs, George Eastman, Walter Prichard Eaton, Richard Henry Edwards, Joseph Fels, Felix Frankfurter, Lewis Gannett, Armand Hammer, Norman Hapgood, Alfred Harcourt, Sidney Hillman, J. J. Jusserand, Paul Underwood Kellogg, Thomas Kirkup, Edward B. Krehbiel, Harry Wellington Laidler, Harold Joseph Laski, Ludwig Lewisohn, Walter Lippmann, Jack London, A. Lawrence Lowell, Julian W. Mack, Paul Elmer More, William Morrow, James Oppenheim, C. H. Parkhurst, Baron Eustace Percy of Newcastle, William Lyon Phelps, John S. Phillips, Charles Mulford Robinson, Edward Alsworth Ross, May Sinclair, William Andrew Spalding, Mark Sullivan, William Simon U'Ren, Lillian D. Wald, Andrew Dickson White, William Winter, and Stephen Samuel Wise.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Family Correspondence, 1863-1924
Correspondence, 1900-1931
Writings File
Subject File, 1917-1929
Miscellany, 1892-1930
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 17,326
- Family Correspondence, 1863-1924 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Letters sent by Gleason to his mother, letters to and from other relatives, and correspondence written and received by his wife, Helen Hayes Gleason.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person and chronologically therein.
  - Gleason, Helen Hayes (wife), letters sent and received, 1914-1919, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Gleason, Leila Seward (mother) and Helen Hayes, copies of extracts of last letters received from Arthur Gleason, 1923 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Gleason, Leila Seward and Henry (parents), 1889 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Gleason, Leila Seward, 1900, 1906, 1915, (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Seward, Will (uncle), 1886 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Seward, Mrs. (?) (grandmother), 1863 (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Correspondence, 1900-1931 (Box 1-4, Reel 1-3)
  Official and personal correspondence written and received by Gleason, including holograph drafts of letters composed by him. Also letters to and from Helen Hayes Gleason concerning her husband's death and the publication of a volume memorializing his writings and achievements.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1900-1911, (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1912 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Jan.-Sept. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Oct.-Dec. (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 1913, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - 1914-1921, (8 folders) (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - 1922 (Box 2, Reel 2)
    - Feb.-Sept. (Box 2, Reel 2)
    - Oct.-Dec. (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - 1923, (4 folders) (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - 1924-1931, (2 folders) (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Undated and incomplete (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - By Gleason (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - Unidentified (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Extracts of letters to editors concerning Gleason's writings, 1912-1923, (3 folders) (Box 4, Reel 3)
- Writings File (Box 4-9, Reel 3-6)
  Typescripts of articles, poems, and interviews by Gleason as well as notes, reflections, and drafts of articles. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Holograph and typewritten manuscripts of writings by others filed at the end of the series are arranged alphabetically by name of the writer.
  - By Gleason, undated (Box 4, Reel 3)
    - "A-Dan", (40 folders) (Box 4, Reel 3)
    - "Dar-Inters", (47 folders) (Box 5, Reel 3-4)
    - "Interv-Plac", (48 folders) (Box 6, Reel 4)
    - "Play-Theo", (44 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5)
    - "Ther-Y", (41 folders) (Box 8, Reel 5)
    - Unidentified, incomplete, and miscellaneous, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 8, Reel 5, Box 9, Reel 5-6)
  - By others, undated (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Bryce, Viscount James Bryce (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Chesterton, G. K., (2 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Cook, Joe (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Furuseth, Andrew, (5 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Gleason, Helen Hayes, (4 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Lamplough, J. S., (4 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Smillie, Robert (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Steinmetz, Charles P. (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Tolstoĭ, Ili͡a L'vovich, graf (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
- Subject File, 1917-1929 (Box 10, Reel 6)
  Minutes, reports, notes, memoranda, contracts, and testimonials.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or name of organization.
  - The Book of Arthur Gleason, miscellaneous material used for publication, 1924-1929 (Box 10, Reel 6)
  - Book publishing agreements, 1917-1919 (Box 10, Reel 6)
  - Bureau of Industrial Research and United Mine Workers, 1921-1923, (2 folders) (Box 10, Reel 6)
  - International Labor Convention (Third Internationale?), incomplete report of second day of labor meeting, undated (Box 10, Reel 6)
  - Memorials to Gleason, 1923-1925 (Box 10, Reel 6)
  - Workers' Trust Agreement establishing organization to promote education among wage earners, 1922 (Box 10, Reel 6)
- Miscellany, 1892-1930 (Box 10-13, Reel 6-8)
  Newspaper and periodical clippings, pamphlets, maps, calling cards, postcards, programs, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and topic.
  - Clippings (Box 10, Reel 6)
    - British Labor and the War, reviews and comments, 1919 (Box 10, Reel 6)
    - Golden Lads, reviews and comments, 1916 (Box 10, Reel 6)
    - Inside the British Isles, reviews and comments, 1917 (Box 10, Reel 6)
    - Irish Commission (American), 1920 (Box 10, Reel 6)
    - Scrapbook, 1923-1930 (Box 11, Reel 6-7)
    - Smillie, Robert, 1919-1923 (Box 11, Reel 6-7)
    - What the Workers Want, reviews and comments, 1920 (Box 11, Reel 6-7)
    - Writings about (Box 11, Reel 6-7)
      - Gleason, Arthur, circa 1912-1920, (3 folders) (Box 11, Reel 6-7)
      - Gleason, Helen Hayes, circa 1914-1928 (Box 11, Reel 6-7)
    - Writings by Arthur Gleason (Box 11, Reel 6-7)
      - circa 1893-1920, (3 folders) (Box 11, Reel 6-7)
      - 1914-1923, (4 folders) (Box 12, Reel 7)
    - Writings by and about Arthur Gleason, circa 1914-1918 (Box 12, Reel 7)
    - Writings by Helen Hayes Gleason, circa 1914-1918 (Box 12, Reel 7)
    - Miscellaneous, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 12, Reel 7, Box 13, Reel 8)
  - Printed matter (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - Calling cards, postcards, and miscellany, 1903-1924, undated (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - Pamphlets on socialism, coal, and industrialism, 1892-1923 (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - Programs, 1918-1919 (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - William Henry Gleason, a memorial volume by his family, 1894 (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - World War I, 1914-1915 (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1916-1922, undated (Box 13, Reel 8)